hello everyone and welcome to another
broadcast of holotalk I'm here today
with O's yetkin who is president and CEO
of yetkin tele systems and Oz is going
Coast to Coast here in the United States
and he he searching three-dimensional
Imaging systems and he's here in the
studio with us today how are you today
O's I'm great Frank thank you very much
if I could just have you hold the
microphone up close there we go I
thought it would be interesting for you
to come on the show to let listeners
know something about some of the
competing technologies that holography
is facing with three-dimensional Imaging
and I know you've gone around the
country and you've seen some of these
startling three-dimensional effects
that's being created by other systems
what are some of those systems like and
how does holography compare to them sure
let me summarize I actually have been
working with these 3D Technologies for a
while I worked on them with NASA for a
while and it's always been an interest
of mine the easiest system that people
can approach right now are LCD shutter
glasses these are glasses these are
electronic glasses that works either
with a monitor a CIT monitor that's
capable of high refresh rates or with
what some of the newer projectors that
can support refresh rates of about 100hz
or 120 hertz the basic principle is that
the monitor displays left and right eye
images
in succession it's called frame
sequential stereo
and the glasses alternately block out
the right and left eye thus giving the
user the illusion of 3D inside the
monitor
problem the main problem with these is
one you need a graphics card capable of
driving them and two you if your refresh
rate is not high enough it gives you a
headache you can see the flicker from
fluorescent lights however most 3D
Technologies right now are based on this
or something similar to it and you know
I'm looking to resell some of these
Technologies so I shouldn't Dash them
too much but
um
e-dimensional is a company that makes
the cheaper version of these glasses
crystallized on the other I mean you
know that's about 100 200 per pair on
the other side of the spectrum is
crystallized which you know places like
NASA use which have the better quality
this is you know starting at the low end
that at the higher end you have similar
systems you have dual projector
stereographic Vision systems
places like IMAX and some other movie
theaters use this this is where you take
two projectors either film or electronic
you stack them together with polarizing
filters on each of them and should the
image
non-depolarizing screen so it has to be
a special kind of a screen like a Silver
Screen that's not necessarily cheap but
a lot of movie theaters might be
equipped with them
um you wear what are called passive
polarized glasses where each
um
each side of the glasses blocks a part
of the image thus you get an illusion of
stereo the advantage to that is you get
very nice excuse me you get very nice
depth you get very nice stereo you might
get some glossing if it's not set up
properly they're kind of expensive
that's the ghosting would be I guess a
registration issue right well it can be
a registration issue but more
importantly it's an issue of a polarizer
not being perfect I see and you know
there are different types of polarizers
there is linear polarization and
circular polarization which I won't go
into simply because my physics is not
enough to explain it but these are the
this is what you have to do if you have
a large movie theater otherwise you can
get to a very very very expensive
um
stereo projector that can do say 120 or
144 Hertz
and have the electronic glasses to go
with that I know there's a company
called real D that's doing something
like that that has really
high power projectors there's something
called the Z screen that goes in front
of the projector turning that frame
sequential stereo to something that can
be viewed with regular passive polarized
glasses so these are the Technologies in
that realm there's also something else
I'm actually reselling this it's the
aerosava p240 monitor now this is on a
more personal scale rather than a
theater scale that's correct so this
takes the same idea and
actually does away with the need to have
a very high refresh rate what this
technology uses is
you know LCD panels are already
polarized I mean they'll see the LCD
technology uses polarization to block
off
the right type of for white to make the
picture so this monitor polarizes the
picture it pixels alternately so for
example even pixels might be the image
for the left eye odd pixels might be the
image for the right eye oh that's
interesting and very very simple too
it's I mean it's very simple in concept
I'm sure it's not easy to use that
registration so these monitors and there
are a couple other companies making them
I believe this is the only one I'm
familiar with they are monitor they only
require passive polarized glasses the
the advantage is you know you get really
good depth you get a very clear image
and you don't have flicker disadvantages
you still need a certain viewing angle
you still need to be up in about 15 to
20 degrees of the image but that's
actually a good solution you know
ranging from two to four thousand
dollars as far as I know um still get a
very I mean it's a personal system it's
the price point has gone down from the
professional to the personal I see
because you know larger projector
systems you know there is a projector
right now the dev queue projector that's
around four thousand dollars but the
larger systems used by places like NASA
go from 30 000 up
so this is more much more of a personal
uh thing that you could have in your uh
home I have two in my office they're
wonderful I can watch 3D movies with
them they work really well with uh 3D
interleaved LEDs of which so you you
don't have to have program material
that's been specifically encoded
to be placed on the screen well you do
actually software out there that takes
regular DVDs and tries to convert them
into three I see it's like a conversion
process and the converted DVDs are not
ever as good as a movie something that
would be shot yeah but it actually does
well what is easier to do is to take a
3D image source for example
to take a game and actually intercept
the graphics rendering Pipeline and
extract those two images and there are
drivers to do that so you can take a
game like World of Warcraft download the
download a five dollar driver and
actually use it with this monitor okay
you know play the game in 3D or you
could have if you have for example a
stereo microscopy application you know
those dysetic microscopes that surgeons
use
you can
put cameras on the microscope and have a
live feed and I know
several surgical
teams and several medical schools have
used the technology to train surgeons
you know because when you see for
example the brain surgery being
performed in 3D it looks a lot it looks
like it's got a lot more information on
your brain surgeon than 2D but I can I
you know any biology background I can
actually see that depth as actually see
that value okay in 3D so that's the
polarized kind of displays whether you
know active shutter glasses or passive
polarized and they run the gamut from
large theatrical Productions all the way
down to something personal just for an
individual as far as your scope now
there is another type of technology
these are the auto stereoscopic monitors
and I think
these are the displays that actually try
to compete with holography okay so these
are um usually not always but usually
based on lenticular screen technology
this is when the monitor or the monitor
it could also be a print has micropisms
in front of it with each
directing a strip of the image you have
to interleave the image properly for
this each
direct a strip of the image to a
different viewing Zone So within about
20 or 30 degrees you have eight or nine
different images you're viewing kind of
like what you do with a stereogram okay
the advantages you don't need glasses to
see it and you can print these pretty
cheap
ly print these
get a sheet for maybe like two dollars
from micro lines or a similar supplier
registered on your sheet and you know
have some depth you've probably seen
these I've seen them in commercial
applications I think already with a few
fast food places on their large menu uh
displays and things am I correct about
that because you're absolutely curious
about that you probably have seen them
on gift cards cereal boxes there was a
company called nishika in the 80s and up
to the early 90s or with the camera yeah
they had a camera it was wonderful it
was a very high uh lines per inch kind
of a
they made for you from the images you
sent unfortunately that company of
yourself gone out of business but I'm
actually going to go down uh to North
Carolina to talk some micro lines about
this technology in my survey of 3D
technology
um so this is easier to work with the
monitors are approaching affordable I
three or four years ago I looked at the
synthogram monitor which was based on
this technology it was pretty good it
did not have as much depth as I would
have liked it to have for the
application we needed at the time
so it did not have as much depth or
clarity as the shutter glasses however
something like that is wonderful for a
marketing kind of
have to put in the display window and
you know people going by see it the
disadvantage and the biggest
disadvantage for this is you sacrifice
resolution right or depth so if you have
nine different viewing zones that cuts
the resolution of each viewing Zone in
nine so with those monitors for example
the centergram was built on a 3200 to
2400 uh LCD monitor if you pulled
properly but when you were playing a 3D
image you couldn't really read text on
it you didn't that's interesting yeah
and the viewing zones are limited so
once you get off the viewings on you get
into the new viewings on there is a
shift now there are advances being made
in this field with eye tracking other
stereoscopic monitors the advantages you
no longer have the viewing zones the
monitor follows changes itself to follow
where the viewer is this is that the
disadvantage is that you have
um
yeah only one person who's able to view
this thing at the time at one time and
makes sense out of it I see now there's
another kind of technology that ogma
sees I should mention it's head track
as your listeners know holographs have
parallax
and they should know that and if they
don't I'd be very disappointed in them
maybe they should be little things but
Holograms have very good Parallax both
vertical and horizontal
and um that's why they can be viewed by
multiple people at the same time most of
these Technologies do not have Parallax
more most of these Technologies
have only one image the lenticular
screens and lenticular prints have some
Parallax you know say as much as a
stereogram that you might make about
eight nine images I have in them with
more than that
but to compensate for that there are
systems that require the user to wear a
head tracker this is a fixed degree of
Freedom tracker that tracks the user's
location in space because and how their
head is oriented and the computer is
instructed to change the scene so I mean
if you have that information if you're
driving this from a 3D application and
so that you get the illusion of looking
at something like a hologram for example
there is a system called The Cave which
is three to six walls of stereo
that the user is immersed in when you're
inside that and you put on those LCD
shutter glasses with a Tracker attached
to them you're basically in something
resembling the Holodeck it's very
convincing you can you know using a
three-dimensional Mouse you can grab
objects you can walk around objects you
can look under objects
so this is a way to augment these
systems to make them more convincing but
where would someone go to experience
something like this the cave you know I
know it has to have several oh I see uh
several uh universities have them
um a more affordable system is the
immersive desk which is a one wall
version of this I see um unfortunately I
don't know if there are any commercially
available systems for this okay actually
there are two more Technologies I forgot
to mention
there are hidden mounts of this place
which I'm sure everybody's heard of I
mean when people think virtual reality
yeah so these helmets usually work with
the head tracking what they have are two
different monitors embedded inside the
helmet that you put on and there is head
tracking so you are essentially immersed
inside the world inside the spiritual
World
these are becoming more affordable I
know there are uh helmets under a
thousand dollars right now I have yet to
do our eyeglasses which are quite
popular the problem with the cheaper hm
is the limited field of view
it's not quite like being inside the
world it's more like being inside the
world looking at looking through welding
goggles when you get the stereo you get
the stereo Vision you get the head
tracking and you can move around
but it's they're kind of heavy and I
have not seen any hmvs right now that
are very good that you know I would mind
spending three four hours in
um if you if somebody does want to
experience this however there are
various uh really high-end video arcades
that feature these one I can think of
off the top of my head is Disney Quest
at the near the Epcot Center not inside
Disney World itself
near Downtown Disney in Orlando they
have a place called Disney Quest which
was about a five to six Story game video
arcade and there are some systems there
featuring hmds which are actually very
entertaining there's the Magic Carpet I
mean this was a couple years ago there
was one game that was immersive where
you had something like a sword and you
were battling cartoon characters okay
that's the most immersive game I've ever
played so there is this technology and
you know I'm hoping the price will come
down because
really wonderful applications would be
enabled with high quality head mounted
displays yeah I think they're working on
something with cycling for training they
have something now that runs off of a PC
and you look at a monitor and you can
buy rods like the Tour de France and
whatever but they're working on a helmet
so that you can be immersed into the
environment that you're cycling in and
trainer that you're working on that you
attach the bike to is controlled by the
computer as well so if you start to go
up a hill there's more resistance
applied to the bicycle on the trainer
and you actually feel like you're going
up a hill resist s wise anyway heart
rate goes up breathing rate goes up that
would be a great application for
something like that and there are
several Sports training I did not know
about that that sounds very neat there
are several applications like this uh
one of them was I saw at a conference
was from the University of Hawaii they
had a virtual beach now I don't know why
anybody would need a virtual beach in
Hawaii but they were trying to treat
post-traumatic stress syndrome you know
with full immersion um now I'm for what
I'm rooting for this kind of Technology
because I love to have a helmet you know
I could plug in and you know program
virtual worlds in I don't think we're
there yet in the civilian world I think
there are really higher end hmds like
twenty thousand dollars and up that have
the field of view required for full
immersion but for actual immersion for
the most holic-like experience the best
thing I've seen is the cave and it's
related Technologies that's stereo I'll
see each other glass stereo with head
tracking now I did see one amazing
display at siggraph last year it's a
very Bachelor Graphics conference yes
everybody comes and showcases their
Technologies and Professor paper there's
been some Holograms there over the years
as well I might have seen that there was
one hologram base there was a company
called rabbit Hall that had very
focusing yeah uh three that had a very
convincing 3D hologram I think they're
on the more expensive side but you
probably know more about those than I do
what I saw was a display called the
holographica well it's made by a company
called holographica from Hungary and
this is a very large display using the
holographic Optical element has its
screen I see I don't know much more
about this technology except that it
supports 64 viewing zones requiring at
this time 64 projectors but the what the
image you see is amazing I mean the
image you see is basically without
glasses this 3D animated thing floating
in space and I think their price and you
know I hope these companies don't get
mad at me everybody loves those uh
floating space images right yeah and
this is what people expect but you
almost they almost had I mean you're
still looking at a screen obviously yeah
and I think their price was about a 350
000 okay there's Advantage being you
need a whole room and the whole cluster
of living species rendering this yeah
now none of these displays to the best
of my knowledge have things like Focus
information they don't capture the phase
information that's coming from uh that
hologram captures are you speaking in
referring about depth of field well when
you say that doesn't feel then the
ability to focus on different parts of
the image oh I see now there may be work
going on in this field that I'm not
aware of where people are working on uh
this kind of information but there are
things in real life in 3D that you take
for granted for example if you were to
hold your finger in front of your eyes
and look at it you see that your eyes
Converge on it and everything else
becomes double vision yes you look
further away your finger yes you see two
fingers I mean this is a part of the
visual cues that you get in the real
world this is what you're used to even
though it's not immediately apparent
that you lack it when you're watching an
IMAX movie but this ultimately causes
eye strain so a hologram capturing every
single thing that's coming from the
object perhaps except the color doesn't
have this so it's got that Clarity that
you can't necessarily have in these uh
other
obviously Hogans are really not
competing with these systems since you
don't have
um
full commotion Holograms yet
um by the way there is another exotic
kind of technology and your listeners
might be familiar with this called uh
volumetric displays this is when you're
where you're spinning a screen very fast
okay and projecting images on it so that
inside that space you know you have 3D
but the one I saw was done with the DLP
projector running at 240 hertz oh I see
but I I'm sure they've been down with
the LCD arrays I think they've been done
with lasers okay you know they look
commencing but it's mostly with the line
art or whatever or I it is I've seen
video with a DLP version I saw a Sig
graph there was actual black and white
video of a man running oh I see okay
which was amazing which was like a full
motion holograph in space except of
course you can't reach into it but I
think that technology and uh the
hardware to support it this a little
little ways off yet do you ever do any
searches on the web to find holographic
displays and then see that what you're
looking at really isn't a hologram that
it's some other type of display and it's
just being called a hologram and you
know are you finding that a lot I I'm
finding that quite a bit everything
that's 3D it calls this alcohol graphic
I mean from the Illusion for example the
other series comic display I got was
called a synthet I mean that's a
intentional allusion to a hologram to um
there are these displays that have
literally smoke and mirrors I mean they
have some sort of Mis projected into
space yeah they projected image and they
say holographic image on Al Gore was
doing those uh state of the World
concerts it is said he appeared as a
hologram in Tokyo what they used was a
goes kind of a fabric with his image
projected down to it I mean so far from
holography that it's not even funny that
they can even call it a hologram and I I
still can't be I don't remember his name
now there's been arguments on the web
that that was a hologram and it's like
it's enough to drive people insane
especially if you're a holographic I'm
sure it drives you insane you know uh
I've seen let's see uh I've seen the
cases they're referred to as holographic
which you know I can kind of buy I mean
it's not holographic obviously but uh
you know you have the same kind of
Parallax so it's some
I'll see each other glasses I got were
tossing themselves as a holographic 3D
experience from your PC I see which is
not the only system I saw that I thought
was doing this which is that is the
holographica system which does use a
holographic element in it okay
um but yeah that must be annoying to you
it must be and and there wasn't the
whole graphic holography Community yeah
well it's getting worse that's uh it's
it's very difficult because it's more
difficult because of a public
expectations of what a hologram should
be when they come to see a hologram and
it's not floating around the room and
it's not being projected somewhere and
it's beautiful three-dimensional images
on a wall
but that doesn't seem to count anymore
now talk to George Lucas I think
Princess Leia ruined it for you
she's the culprit right yeah I mean that
photographic projection from R2D2 I
think that's what people expect yeah
that's I think that's what started a lot
of I mean there there had been some
films where Holograms have been in the
films before that
um but I think Star Wars was what uh
what probably started that notion of
what a hologram should be as far as
something
ejected out in space
who knows maybe someday we will get a
technology that is capable of projecting
images out in space
I've heard of things proposed with
intersecting high power lasers in there
and Heating
air so that moves plasma is still there
yeah I don't know if those will ever
happen but they still won't be Holograms
yeah well the thing is you know light
doesn't stop anywhere you know it
continues to move it's you can't send it
out 12 feet and tell it to stop and form
something but I I've heard of what
you're referring to as far as
ionizing the air you know where the two
lasers intersect but then you've got
lasers that continue on after that
intersection point so I'm not quite sure
and I don't know what that would look
like around such a display when it's
running I'll keep my safe distance and
my heart from a distance yeah so what's
your future plans you're working with
holography here in the lab
and you've seen Holograms what's your uh
you've done holography in high school
that's that's right that's right early
on that so I I have to thank Mr van my
physics teacher from Wauwatosa West for
giving me the opportunity and getting me
you know started on this
um
my plans are I've started yet can tell
assistance which is a 3D products and
services company I want to offer all
sorts of
um 3D products ranging from these
relatively expensive you know I'd say
they're cheap of course since they're
not thirty thousand dollars like these
four thousand dollar projectors to you
know three dollar view master style
cardboard viewers and I'm going to offer
all of these Technologies hopefully
holography as well to my clients uh in
Turkey I'm I'm starting the company over
there or in the United States as the
case may be who are interested in not
only just buying these things but also
integrating them with whatever they're
doing so for example
might offer 3D movie theaters for hotels
for higher end hotels using these
projector Technologies I might go to an
arcade and you know set them up with the
3D monitors or set them up with a real
projected you know 3D system where you
know with some head tracking where their
users feel like they're inside the game
you know they can basically creating
miniature versions of these caves and
immersive desks that you know are in the
you know some ten thousand dollar range
um I'm hoping with the Holograms to sell
them to companies
uh yeah Frank has this wonderful way of
doing uh logos uh with a relatively
simple process from a computer image
that fought in space I think that has
that has potential as a really cool
novelty until it's actually market and
I've never seen them so you know it's
the market is pretty empty of those I
would love to offer and be able to do
Holograms you know custom holographs for
companies with their logos and such
um well they're good for trade shows
conventions you know when they have a
booth or something the one that I have
over here on the wall was actually used
in Dusseldorf Germany for a book fair
you know book convention worldwide book
convention and it's basically for a draw
you know you you want to get people to
your booth you want to get people to get
your company's information so they
actually the Holograms I did for them
were 30 by 40 centimeter that's an eight
by ten there but they put those in their
booths and they had people you know
standing around looking at this logo
floating out in space and their sales
people could go out and you know
approach them to give them information
about the company at this point in time
in 2007 I think anything 3D still draws
crowds at trade shows for example a
thick graph you know the rabbit hole
company that had a full color or you
know seemingly full color hologram had
people congregated around it asking the
owner what this was I mean they couldn't
even figure out it was a hologram so you
know for anybody trying to differentiate
their product I think or differentiate
themselves as a place like a trade show
or even a shop it's a great conversation
piece it's a great uh crowd draw I mean
you say on your web page vanity is like
the ultimate marketing tool well it is
in a sense you know but I mean I'd love
to have that with myself that's why I
say that yeah but you know I basically
going to spend the gamut of 3D products
and services and hopefully you know
bring it to a place where it really
hasn't been that popular in in the past
I want to thank you for being on the
show I'm sure the listeners found what
you have to say about 3D competing
Technologies very interesting I think
they may be already aware of some of
them but you may have had you know a few
in there that they hadn't heard of
before and some of the ones that they
did hear of you probably clarified a few
things for them but out of all the
Technologies including holography I
would have to ask you this before we
close the show which one gives you the
best
visual three-dimensional space well I
think holography is untouched in terms
of clarity right now you know if you
want to see something that's as real as
the object I mean holography is a holy
grail and I think you know these people
who are working on those Technologies
myself included understand this that's
why everybody is saying you know the our
technology has holographic Clarity it's
a whole graphic experience you know the
whole Holograms don't substitute for
things like interactive 3D which most of
these Technologies are geared towards
but if you had to Archive like Museum
materials I think holography is the way
to go that's interesting because there's
a conference coming up in London next
year on archiving Museum materials from
the Hologram you could probably go to
all these other Technologies yes well I
want to thank you for being on the show
taking taking your time and the two of
us are now going to go over to the
holography table and we're going to do
some work and thank you for listening to
the show and hope you tune in for each
new installment as they become available
here at holotalk so thank you and good
night